American Medical Center for Burma Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
American Medical Center for Burma Records 1945-1966 (bulk 1959-1965)
MSS48058
American Medical Center for Burma
9,000 items 35 containers plus 1 oversize 7 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Organization incorporated and based in New York to support Gordon Stifler Seagrave and the Namkham Hospital in Burma. Correspondence, administrative and financial records, clippings, magazines, subject files, maps, and other papers relating mainly to Seagrave's medical work in Burma.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Brown, Rothwell H.--Correspondence.; Dooley, Thomas A. (Thomas Anthony), 1927-1961.; Ellison, Fanny McConnell--Correspondence.; Everton, John Scott--Correspondence.; Key, David McKendree, 1900-1988--Correspondence.; Newhall, Joseph F.--Correspondence.; Newhall, Ruth--Correspondence.; Olmanson, Barbara--Correspondence.; Olmanson, Myron Donald--Correspondence.; Oram, Harold L., 1907-1990--Correspondence.; Radvin, R. S.--Correspondence.; Reinholt, Haldor--Correspondence.; Rich, John F.--Correspondence.; Seagrave, Gordon Stifler, 1897-1965--Correspondence.; Seagrave, Gordon Stifler, 1897-1965.; Seagrave, Marion--Correspondence.; Seagrave, Sterling--Correspondence.; Wilson, Howard P.--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Medical Center for Burma.; Midwives and Nurses Training School (Namkhan, Burma); Namkham Hospital.; Peace Corps (U.S.)
Subjects
Hospitals--Burma--Namkhan.; Medicine--Burma--Namkhan.; Nurses--Burma--Namkhan.
Places
Burma--Politics and government.; Namkhan (Burma)--History.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The records of the American Medical Center for Burma, an organization incorporated and based in New York to support Gordon Stifler Seagrave and the Namkham Hospital in Burma, were given to the Library of Congress by the center in 1966-1967 Additional material was given by Weston Seagrave in 1967 and by Esther N. Mertins in 1968.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the America Medical Center for Burma Records.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the American Medical Center for Burma are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Gordon Stifler Seagrave
Date Event
1897, Mar. 18 Born, Rangoon, Burma
1917 A.B., Denison University, Granville, Ohio
1920 Married Marion Grace Morse
1921 M.D., Johns Hopkins University Medical School, Baltimore, Md.
1922-1965 Practiced medicine, Namkham Hospital, Namkhan, Burma, with a four-year absence from 1942 to 1946
1930 Published Waste-Basket Surgery. Philadelphia and Boston: Judson Press
1938 Published Tales of a Waste-Basket Surgeon. Philadelphia and Boston: Judson Press
1942-1946 Served in United States Army Medical Corps, first as Major and later as Lieutenant Colonel
1943 Published Burma Surgeon. New York: W.W. Norton and Co.
1946 Published Burma Surgeon Returns. New York: W.W. Norton and Co.
1955 Published My Hospital in the Hills. New York: W.W. Norton and Co.
1960 Published Life of a Burma Surgeon. New York: Ballantine Books
1965, Mar. 29 Died, Namkhan, Burma
Scope and Content Note
The records of the American Medical Center for Burma span the years 1945-1966, with the bulk of the material falling between 1959-1965. The American Medical Center for Burma, with a main office in New York, was a nonsectarian, nonprofit organization founded in 1946 to support the Namkham Hospital and Midwives and Nurses Training School founded by Gordon Stifler Seagrave, the famed "Burma Surgeon," in Namkhan, Burma, in 1922. The American Medical Center for Burma was reorganized in 1959 to give even greater financial support to Seagrave and the Namkham Hospital. The records of the American Medical Center for Burma consist primarily of correspondence between Seagrave and the staff, officers, and Board of Directors of the organization and are organized into the following series: General Correspondence, Special Correspondence, Financial Contributors' Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, Printed Matter, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize. The main body of correspondence is supported by administrative files of the organization, newspaper clippings, printed matter, financial records, and a galley proof of one of Seagrave's books, Life of a Burma Surgeon, published in 1960 by Ballantine Books.
The correspondence between the American Medical Center for Burma and Seagrave for the years 1946-1954 was originally held by the W. W. Norton Publishing Company and is the smallest segment of the records. With the reorganization of the American Medical Center for Burma in 1959, the records and files become more detailed and comprehensive. Following the death of Seagrave in 1965, the American Medical Center for Burma dissolved itself as a corporate entity.
Because Seagrave's personal papers were destroyed during World War II, the records of the American Medical Center for Burma became the only readily available source of material concerning Seagrave and his work at the Namkham Hospital. After his death, the Namkham Hospital was nationalized by the Burmese government. Any records at the hospital then became the possession of the Burmese government.
The records are rich in material concerning the last twenty years of Seagrave's life. His activities as a physician, his role in American foreign policy, and his financial difficulties with the hospital, with the procurement of supplies for the hospital, and with the Burmese government, are documented in the collection. His correspondence with the staff, officials, and Board of Directors of the American Medical Center for Burma, and his correspondence with his family and with members of the Burmese government, copies of which are generally included in the American Medical Center for Burma's files, indicate the problems involved in supporting, administering, and directing this charitable institution.
The files of the American Medical Center for Burma are concerned not only with Seagrave directly, but also with the problem of fund-raising and the financial support of the Namkham Hospital. The records contain correspondence, notes, and memoranda exchanged by members of the organization with officials of the Burmese government and members of the hospital staff at Namkham, especially the American doctors and their spouses who were sent to Burma by the American Medical Center for Burma to aid and assist Seagrave.
Of special interest in this collection is correspondence concerning the growth of the American Peace Corps in the 1960s, Thomas A. Dooley, revolutions in some of the semi-autonomous states of Burma against the central government, and the difficulties encountered by foreigners traveling or living in Burma.
In addition to Seagrave other correspondents include Joseph F. Newhall, Ruth Newhall, Barbara Olmanson, Myron Donald Olmanson, Marion Seagrave, and Sterling Seagrave. The collection also contains the correspondence of members of the American Medical Center for Burma such as Rothwell H. Brown, Fanny McConnell Ellison, John Scott Everton, David McKendree Key, Harold L. Oram, R. S. Radvin, Haldor Reinholt, John F. Rich, and Howard P. Wilson.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
General Correspondence, 1946-1965
Special Correspondence, 1955-1966
Financial Contributors' Correspondence, 1946-1965
Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1965
Printed Matter, 1948-1965
Miscellany, 1946-1963
Addition, 1947-1964
Oversize, circa 1962
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78048058
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1946-1965 (Box 1-5)
  Letters to and from Seagrave and the staff, officials, and Board of Directors of the American Medical Center for Burma.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1946-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960-1961, Aug. (Box 3)
  - 1961, Sept.-1963, Aug. (Box 4)
  - 1963, Oct.-1965 (Box 5)
- Special Correspondence, 1955-1966 (Box 6-12)
  Administrative correspondence files of the American Medical Center for Burma.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and therein chronologically.
  - American Council of Voluntary Agencies for Foreign Service (Box 6)
  - American Medical Center for Burma Bulletin (Box 6)
  - Applications for Namkham Hospital personnel (Box 6)
  - Ballantine Books (Box 6)
  - Board of Directors (Box 7)
  - Brown, Rothwell H. (Box 7)
  - Burma (Box 7)
  - China-Burma-India Roundup (Box 7)
  - College fund-raising (Box 7)
  - Columbia Broadcasting System (Box 8)
  - Committee for the Distribution of Medical Aid Received from Overseas (Box 8)
  - Everton, John S. (Box 8)
  - Executive committee (Box 8)
  - Fortieth anniversary of Seagrave (Box 8)
  - "Frontier Medicine at the Namkham Hospital" (Box 9)
  - Fund-raising legislation (Box 9)
  - Hollingsworth, Dr. and Mrs. R. T. (Box 9)
  - Honorary awards (Box 9)
  - Internationally Yours (Box 9)
  - Inter-office memoranda (Box 9)
  - Key, David M. (Box 9)
  - Letters to the editor (Box 9)
  - Marshall, Clifford B. (Box 9)
  - Medical advisory council (Box 9)
  - Moses, Mrs. Henry L. (Box 9)
  - Motion picture benefits (Box 10)
  - Nathan, Robert R. (Box 10)
  - Newhall, Dr. and Mrs. Joseph (Box 10)
  - Norton, W. W. (Box 10)
  - Olmanson, Dr. and Mrs. Donald (Box 10)
  - One Hundred and One Association (Box 10)
  - Prioleau fund-raising drive (Box 11)
  - Public relations (Box 11)
  - Radvin, Dr. R. S. (Box 11)
  - Reader's Digest (Box 11)
  - Reinholt, Haldor (Box 11)
  - Rich, John and staff (Box 12)
  - Robb, Inez (Box 12)
  - Rockefeller, John D., 1937- (Box 12)
  - Rusk, Howard A. (Box 12)
  - Saturday Evening Post (Box 12)
  - Smith, Forrest (Box 12)
  - Television and motion picture proposals (Box 12)
  - Trader Vic benefit (Box 12)
  - Time-Life publications (Box 12)
  - Travel in Burma (Box 12)
  - Walker, Dr. W. L. (Box 12)
  - Wilson, Howard P. (Box 12)
- Financial Contributors' Correspondence, 1946-1965 (Box 13-14)
  Correspondence and records concerning donations received from the public and replies to the donors.
  - 1946-1962 (Box 13)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 14)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1965 (Box 15-16)
  Newspaper clippings concerning Seagrave and the Namkham Hospital.
  - 1959-1961 (Box 15)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 16)
- Printed Matter, 1948-1965 (Box 17)
  Magazines, articles, press clippings and releases, pamphlets, and journals concerning Seagrave.
  - 1948-1965 (Box 17)
- Miscellany, 1946-1963 (Box 18)
  Memoranda, financial records, maps, and galley proofs.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Financial journal, 1946-1956 (Box 18)
  - Financial records, 1948-1956 (Box 18)
  - Galley proof of Life of a Burma Surgeon (Box 18)
  - Map of Burma, annotated (Box 18)
  - Memoranda, records, and financial accounts for Nurses Training School, Namkhan, Burma, 1958-1963 (Box 18)
- Addition, 1947-1964 (Box 19-36)
  Administrative files, corporate records, hospital drawings, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by administrative files and corporate records and therein chronologically.
  - Administrative files (Box 19)
    - Chronological file (Box 19)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 19)
      - 1948-1950 (Box 20)
      - 1950-1953 (Box 21)
      - 1953-1957 (Box 22)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 23)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 24)
      - 1960 (Box 25)
      - 1961 (Box 25)
        - "A-C" miscellaneous (Box 25)
        - "D-J" miscellaneous (Box 26)
        - "K-Z" miscellaneous (Box 27)
      - 1962 (Box 27)
        - "A-B" miscellaneous (Box 27)
        - Board of Directors-Gifts-in-kind (Box 28)
        - "I-Z" miscellaneous (Box 29)
      - 1963 (Box 30)
        - "A" miscellaneous-Board of Directors, David McKey (Box 30)
        - Board of Directors-"M" miscellaneous (Box 31)
        - Mail appeals-"Z" miscellaneous (Box 32)
    - Miscellaneous material including 1964 administrative file, AID file, financial reports, photographs, hospital drawings (circa 1962), and reprints of articles about Seagrave, circa 1962-1964 See also Oversize (Box 33)
  - Corporate records (Box 34-35)
- Oversize, circa 1962 (Box OV 1)
  Hospital drawings.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Addition (Box OV 1)
    - Administrative files (Box OV 1)
      - Chronological file (Box OV 1)
        - Miscellaneous material including 1964 administrative file, AID file, financial reports, photographs, hospital drawings (circa 1962), and reprints of articles about Seagrave, circa 1962 (Container 33) (Box OV 1)